Guide to the Robert Lax Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Robert Lax Papers,
[ca. 1938]-1990
Lax, Robert.
17 linear ft. ( ca. 5,300 items in 31 boxes & 1 package).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079014
Biographical Note
Poet & editor (Columbia University B.A., 1938) who was born in 1915.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, drawings, photographs, and printed material of Lax. Included are letters of Mark and Dorothy Van Doren and Thomas Merton. The bulk of the collection is comprised of Lax's poetry and journal manuscripts, many written in Patmos and Kalymnos, Greece, and originally sent to Emil Antonucci of the Journeyman Press in New York for publication. Also, printed photographs and unprinted negatives of pictures taken by Lax, primarily in Greece.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 17 series:
Series I: Correspondence and Manuscripts
Series II: Uncataloged correspondence and manuscripts by others
Series III: Manuscripts, alphabetical
Series IV: Manuscripts, chronological
Series V: Manuscripts
Series VI: Artwork
Series VII: Photographs
Series VIII: Printed materials
Series IX: Oversize, Art
Series X: Oversize, Manuscripts
Series XI: Uncataloged correspondence and manuscripts by others
Series XII: Manuscripts
Series XIII: Manuscripts, untitled
Series XIV: Manuscripts
Series XV: Photographs
Series XVI: Printed materials
Series XVII: Addition to Lax Papers
Subjects
Journeyman Press (New York, N.Y.); Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972.; Van Doren, Dorothy.; Merton, Thomas, 1915-1968.; Antonucci, Emil.; Greece--Pictorial works.; Patmos Island (Greece)--Description and travel.; Kalymnos (Greece)--Description and travel.; Literature publishing--New York (State)--New York.; American literature--20th century.; American poetry--20th century.; Publishers and publishing--New York (State)--New York.; Drawings.; Journals.; Manuscripts (literary).; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photographs.; Photonegatives.; Photoprints.; Poems.; Sketches.; Authors, American.; Poets, American.; Editors.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1971 M-71 Lax, Robert Gift
10/26/90 M-90-10-26 Letters & clippings Lax, Robert Gift
Gift of Robert Lax, 1971-1975 & 1990.
- Series I: Correspondence and Manuscripts
  - Cataloged correspondence and manuscripts (Box 1)
- Series II: Uncataloged correspondence and manuscripts by others
  - Photocopies of Thomas Merton correspondence & manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III: Manuscripts
  Titled typescripts, in alphabetical order
  - Another play for Nancy Flagg, Sept. 2 1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    [Arranged alphabetically]
- Series IV: Manuscripts, untitled
  Arranged chronologically
  - Poetry volumes, 1941-1959 (Box 10)
  - Poetry volumes (Box 14)
    [Untitled and undated]
  - Poetry volumes and scroll poems (Box 15)
  - Loose poetry [No order apparent] (Box 16 - 20)
  - Journal and prose notes [Arranged chronologically], [n.d.]; 1938-1940 (Box 21)
- Series V: Manuscripts
  - Journals, notebooks, loose writings, [n.d.]; 1965-1968; 1973, 1974 (Box 23)
- Series VI: Artwork
  - Drawings and sketches (Box 24)
- Series VII: Photographs
  Arranged by subject
  - Reinhardt (Box 25, Folder 1)
    [ Black and white, contact sheets, prints of various sizes]
  - Negatives, completely unlabeled and unorganized (Box 26 - 28)
- Series VIII: Printed materials
  - Original and photocopied items written by Lax, including whole journals and other publications, 1968-1973 (Box 29)
- Series IX: Oversize, Art
  - Lax, Robert [Figure in landscape], [n.p.], [n.d.], (8 x 11 [on mat] watercolor) (Box 316)
  - Lax, Robert [Woman], [n.p.], 8 July 1939, (8 x 11 [on mat] watercolor) (Box 316)
- Series X: Oversize, Manuscripts
  - Lax, Robert "The Sea Poem", [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 manuscripts) (Box 316)
- Series XI: Uncataloged correspondence and manuscripts by others
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1944-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Uncataloged correspondence (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Uncataloged correspondence & mss. re: "The Circus of the Stars" (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mss. by Gerhard van den Bergh (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Merton-Lax mss., Book of Merton letters (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Uncataloged mss. by others (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series XII: Manuscripts
  - Arise & be happy & glad... (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Acey-Ducey, Summer 1959 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Acey-Ducey (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Able Charlie Baker Dance (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - A Bower of Weeds (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Fire Water Earth & Air (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Gentle Legend (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Book of Revango (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Circus of the Sun (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Black Yogurt (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fritz (Box 4, Folder 8, 9)
  - Gooper's Landing (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Assumption Day (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mark the Teacher (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Long Horrible Night at Riker's, a play, Jan. 11, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Jack the Cat (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Notebook Blue (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Libretto for a Technicolor Ballet (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - The Morning Stars (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Is-sus Miggs (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Invocation & Canticle (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The Island Kingdom (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Island Kingdom (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - New poems (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Histories (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Omnibus (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Recent works, includes photographs and drawings (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Poems (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Old notebooks (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Once & For All (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - One About the Future (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - One Two Three (1,2,3) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous poems (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Tractatus (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Recollections of a Temple Dancer (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Songs (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Scraps (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Tosca (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Solomon's High Dive (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous poems (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Three Days Patmos, many drafts & copies (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Winter (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - The Voyage to Pescara (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Winter Lightning (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - You Gotta Understand the Language (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Series XIII: Manuscripts, untitled
  - Poetry volumes, 1959-1960 (Box 11)
  - Poetry volumes, 1961-1966 (Box 12)
  - Poetry volumes, 1972-1974 (Box 13)
- Series XIV: Manuscripts
  - Journal and prose notes, 1941-1945 (Box 22)
- Series XV: Photographs
  - Rice (Box 25, Folder 2)
    [Black and white, contact sheets, prints of various sizes]
  - Jubilee (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Ringling (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Alzana (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Bermuda (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Lowe (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Van Doren (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - France; Corps, Eau Vive (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Cristianis (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Brittanic (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - Book of taped in photographs (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Various envelopes of seaside portraits (Box 25)
- Series XVI: Printed materials
  - Original and photocopied items written by Lax, including whole journals and other publications. Also includes music scores and writings by others, mainly poetry journals. 1961-1991 (Box 30)
  - Original and photocopied items written by Lax, including whole journals and other publications. Also includes music scores and writings by others, mainly poetry journals. 1966-1995 (Box 31)
- Series XVII: Addition to Lax Papers
  - Printed materials written by Lax; correspondence with several notable figures, including Richard Avedon and Jack Kerouac; bibliography of his writing and other miscellaneous items. (Box 32)